Guide to the United Cigarette Machine Company records, 1887-1955 and undated RL.01320
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United Cigarette Machine Company records
1887-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United Cigarette Machine Company
RL.01320
40 Linear Feet
Lynchburg, Virginia manufacturing company specializing in cigarette machine and car parts; plants were located in the U.S. and Germany. The bulk of the United Cigarette Machine Company collection, dating from 1887-1955, consists of thousands of brownprints ("Van Dyke photoprints") and blueprints related to the various cigarette machines and parts manufactured by the company. These include the Universal, U-K, Improved Bonsack (designed by James Bonsack), and Heckendorn cigarette machines; materials from the 1920s also pertain to the manufacturing of Buick, Dodge, and Chevrolet auto parts. Other files contain black-and-white photographs of products, and company catalogs. Additional material includes contracts, legal papers, appraisals, audits, patent lists, tax reports, and minutes documenting company operations and finances. The center of operations was located in Lynchburg, Virginia; the company also owned manufacturing plants in Germany. A few materials are in French and German.
Approx. 12,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The United Cigarette Machine Company Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1956.
Collection Overview
The bulk of the United Cigarette Machine Company collection, dating from 1887-1955, consists of thousands of brownprints ("Van Dyke photoprints") and blueprints related to the various cigarette machines and parts manufactured by the company. These include the Universal, U-K, Improved Bonsack (invented by James A. Bonsack), and Heckendorn cigarette machines; materials from the 1920s also pertain to the manufacturing of Buick, Dodge, and Chevrolet auto parts. Other files contain black-and-white photographs of products, and company catalogs. Additional material includes contracts, legal papers, appraisals, audits, patent lists, tax reports, and minutes documenting company operations and finances. The center of operations was located in Lynchburg, Virginia; the company also owned manufacturing plants in Germany. A few materials are in French and German. The United Cigarette Machine Company's main factory in Lynchburg was built in 1907, at the crossing of the Southern Railway main line and the Lynchburg & Durham Railroad line.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged in three series: Company Records, Mechanical Drawings, and Volumes.
Brownprints; Mechanical drawings (tool-aided drawings); Black-and-white photographs; Blueprints; Cigarette industry; Cigarette industry -- Virginia; Machinery -- Drawings; Lynchburg (Va.) -- History; Cigarette industry -- Germany; Cigarette manufacture and trade -- United States; United Cigarette Machine Company; United Cigarette Machine Company; Bonsack, James Albert, 1859-1924
- Company Records Series, 1887-1953 and undated, 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains contracts, legal papers, tax reports, correspondence, minutes, blueprints, and catalogs relating to the United Cigarette Machine Company, and the company's properties in Virginia and Dresden, Germany.
  - Information Folder (Box 1)
    Includes a typed account of James A. Bonsack's invention of the cigarette-making machine written by Bonsack's nephew, John E. Bonsack, 1938.
  - Papers, 1887-1901 (Box 1)
  - Papers re: Durmid [Va.] property, 1887, Oct. 24-1920, May 26 and undated (Box 1)
  - Papers (general), 1903-1909 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1904 (Box 1)
  - Papers (general), United Cigarette Machine Co. vs. W.I. Brown, 1904, Feb. 12-1907, May 15 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1905-1920, Deeds, 1905, July 25-1920, Sept. 15 (Box 1)
  - Papers (general), 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Papers (general), 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Papers (general), 1915 (Box 2)
  - Dead Leases, Durmid, 1915, Dec. 31 (Box 2)
  - Papers (general), 1916-1917 (Box 2)
  - Papers (general), 1918-1919 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Papers relative to the formation of the UCMC GmBH in Dresden, circa 1921 (Box 3)
  - Papers (general), 1922 (Box 3)
  - Papers (general), 1923-1926 (Box 3)
  - Papers (general), 1927-1929 (Box 3)
  - Papers (general), 1930-1953 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1889-1899 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1900-1905 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1906-1910 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1911-1913 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1914-1916 (Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1917-1919 (Box 5)
  - Contracts, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Contracts, 1921 (Box 5)
  - Contracts, 1922 (Box 5)
  - Contracts, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Contracts, 1924 (Box 5)
  - Contracts, 1925 (Box 6)
  - Contracts, 1926 (Box 6)
  - Contracts, 1927 (Box 6)
  - Contracts, 1928-1929 (Box 6)
  - Contracts, 1930-1953 (Box 6)
  - Printed Material (Box 6)
  - Papers (general), undated; Report of Validity, Scope, and Infringement of Items (Box 6)
  - Papers (general), miscellany and undated (Box 6)
- Mechanical Drawings Series, 1896-1948 and undated, 19 boxes
  Mechanical drawings, brownprints ("Vandyke prints"), and blueprints representing cigarette-making machines and car parts designed and manufactured by the United Cigarette Machine Company. Arranged in original order as received, and housed in boxes according to size; therefore, box numbers appear out of sequence.
  - Cigarette-Making Machine Parts Drawings, 1896-1955
    - Untitled set, circa 1896, 26 sheets (Box 7)
    - D33: The Ludington Peerless Cigarette Machine, 1897-31+1900, 31 sheets (Box 7)
    - D-B: The Ludington Unique Cigarette Machine, 1899-1900, 53 sheets (Box 7)
    - UB, 1909, 2 sheets (Box 7)
    - A-F: Automatic Feed, 1909-1922, 53 sheets (Box 7)
    - Elliott Receiver, 1910, 5 sheets (Box 7)
    - E.M.: Ewers cigarette-making machine, 1910-1912, 82 sheets (Box 7)
    - N.L. & M.L., 1910-1920, 16 sheets (Box 7)
    - UM: Universal cigarette-making machine, 1910-1920, 933 sheets (Box 8, 21, 23)
    - United Company's Cut-off, 1914, 4 sheets (Box 8)
    - Stemming Mch., 1914-1915, 31 sheets (Box 8)
    - U.A.: Automatic Feed for the Universal cigarette-making machine (U-M), 1914-1926, 240 sheets (Box 8, 21, 23)
    - UG: Triumph cigarette-making machine, 1915-1940, 3,412 sheets (Box 9, 23-25)
    - Heating Device, 1915, 4 sheets (Box 10)
    - Ewers Hopper Attachment, 1915, 6 sheets (Box 10)
    - UM & UK [no.]-P, or P, 1914-1919, 43 sheets (Box 10)
    - TA: Tipping Device, 1919-1929, 210 sheets (Box 10, 21, 25)
    - U.K.A.: Automatic feeder for the UK cigarette-making machine, 1915-1923, 315 sheets (Box 10, 21, 25)
    - R, or UM & UK [no.]-R: Receiver for Universal and United Koerner cigarette-making machine, 1915-1919, 2 sheets (Box 10)
    - BM: Bonsack machine, 1917-1925, 459 sheets (Box 11, 21, 25)
    - P.C.M., 1917-1921, 9 sheets (Box 11)
    - P, or, PERF: Perfection cigarette-making machine, 1916-1923, 477 sheets (Box 11, 21, 26)
    - H, or HECK: Heckendorn cigarette-making machine, 1916-1918, 851 sheets (Box 11, 21, 26)
    - BTS: Billings Tobacco Stemmer, 1919-1948 (includes parts lists), 1,256 sheets (Box 10-12, 22)
    - Oversize sheets from BTS: Billings Tobacco Stemmer, 1919-1948 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - UK: United Koerner cigarette-making machine, 1906-1930, 1,295 sheets (Box 13-14, 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 1915-1930 and undated, 242 sheets (Box 15, 28)
    - Single Knife Grinder, undated, 9 sheets (Box 15)
    - Old Crimper, undated, 6 sheets (Box 15)
    - Net Cut-Off, undated, 6 sheets (Box 15)
    - Improved Crimper, undated, 4 sheets (Box 15)
    - Improved Bonsack--Not Finished, undated, 7 sheets (Box 15)
    - Hopper Attachment for Bonsack Aut., undated, 2 sheets (Box 15)
    - Double Printer and Bronzer, undated, 8 sheets (Box 15)
    - Details for Printer, undated, 3 sheets (Box 15)
    - Bonsack Roller Part, undated, 11 sheets (Box 15)
    - Bonsack Machine, undated, 4 sheets (Box 15)
    - Bonsack Channel for Universal Machine, undated, 2 sheets (Box 15)
    - A.M.: Cigarette Splitter, undated, 3 sheets (Box 15)
    - T.S.H., 1927, 61 sheets (Box 15)
    - P.E., 1925-1927, 221 sheets (Box 16, 22, 28)
    - AR, 1922-1923, 8 sheets (Box 16)
    - C: Boedicker Phot. Litho. Machine, or, United-Precision Group Negative Machine and Camera, 1921-1950, 222 sheets (Box 16)
    - PM: A machine to put cigarettes into packets of ten or twenty, 1921-1927, 1,730 sheets (Box 17, 29)
    - Bonsack Machine with Automatic Feed: Assembly Draing, 1915, 1 sheet (Box 18)
    - Cigarette Splitting Machines, 1915, 98 sheets (Box 18)
    - Heckendorn Cigarette-Making Machine, 1920-1923, 7 sheets (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Data Concerning Cigarette-Making Machines, 1915-1927 and undated, 52 sheets (Box 18)
    - T.S.V.: Tobacco Cutting Machine, 1914-1940, 18 sheets (Box 18)
    - U.K.: Cigarette-Making Machine, Assembly Drawings, 1916-1921, 6 sheets (Box 18)
    - Winston Cigarette Machine Company: Machine Blueprints, undated, 7 sheets (Box 18)
    - Standard (S.T.A.) Cut-Off: Brownprints, 1927, 163 sheets (Box 19)
    - T.S.V.: Tobacco Cutting Machine, Blueprints, 1923-1929, 466 sheets (Box 19)
    - U.M. and U.K.: Cigarette-Making Machines, Brownprints, 1918-1927, 726 sheets (Box 20)
    - Bonsack Machine: Original Drawings of Old 'Bonsack' Cigarette Making Machine, undated, 53 sheets (Box 22)
    - Hand-Feed Machine, undated, 24 sheets (Box 22)
    - U.G., 1925-1955, 212 sheets (Box 22)
    - S.T.S.: Tobacco Stemming Machine, New Schofield Design, undated, 4 sheets (Box 22)
    - ST.A.: Standard Abschneider, 1927, 8 sheets (Box 28)
  - Car Parts Drawings, 1923-1924
    - Buick Carburetor Parts--Miscellaneous, 1924, 40 sheets (Box 18)
    - Buick High Power Engine, undated, 2 sheets (Box 18)
    - Buick Carburetor for Ford Cars, 1924, 53 sheets (Box 22)
    - Buick Carburetor for Willys-Knight Cars, 1924, 30 sheets (Box 22)
    - Buick High Power Engine, undated, 2 sheets (Box 22)
    - Chevrolet Car Parts: Mostly Buick Carburetor, 1923-1924, 9 sheets (Box 22)
    - Dodge Car Parts, 1924, 5 sheets (Box 22)
    - Overland Car--Choker Body, undated, 1 sheet (Box 22)
- Volumes Series, 1888-1926 and undated, 6 boxes
  Contains handwritten and typed minutes, documents of appraisal, audits, articles of association, ledgers, photographs, catalogs, and legal documents related to the United Cigarette Machine Company's involvement in court cases. Unless otherwise noted, all volumes are undated. Some materials are in French and German.
  - Appraisal (Box 30)
  - Minute book (Box 31)
  - Memorandum and articles of Association of Molins Machine Company Limited, 1912 (Box 31)
  - Certified appraisal (Box 31)
  - Minutes of the Tobacco Stemming Machine Company, 1913-1926 (Box 31)
  - Bonsack Cigarette Machine, list of parts (Box 32)
  - Parts of Bonsack Cigarette Machine, photographed, The Glamorgan Pipe and Foundry Company, Lynchburg, VA (Box 32)
  - Bonsack Machine Co., 1900, Jan. 1, Handwritten notes and clippings (Box 32)
  - Spare parts catalogue of the Triumph Cigarette Machine, first edition, In English, German, and French (Box 32)
  - Spare parts catalogue of the Triumph II Cigarette Machine, first edition, In English, German, and French (Box 32)
  - The United Cigarette Machine Company Limited, Memorandum and Articles of Association, 1899 (Box 33)
  - D.E. Ledger (Box 33)
  - Ledger (Box 33)
  - Catalog for the UK Cigarette Machine, fourth edition, In English, French, and German (Box 33)
  - List of patents, 1921 (Box 33)
  - Catalog for the Universal Cigarette Machine, fourth edition, In English, French, and German (Box 34)
  - Report on audit, 1918 (Box 34)
    For year ending December 31, 1916 and year ending December 31, 1917.
  - Restatement of accounts, 1920 (Box 34)
  - Fiftieth Congress--First Session, House Bill 593: An Act for the Relief of Jas. A. Bonsack, Affidavits of James A. Bonsack and Others, 1888 (Box 34)
  - U.S. Circuit Court, Northern District, N.Y.: Bonsack Machine Company against Allison Brothers Company, Master's Report, 1891 (Box 34)
  - Fiftieth Congress--First Session, House Bill 593: Note of Argument--No. 3, 1888 (Box 34)
  - U.S. Circuit Court at Lynchburg: E.T. Pollard vs. The Bonsack Machine Company, Note of Argument for the defendant by Robt. E. Scott (Box 34)
  - U.S. Circuit Court, Northern District, N.Y.: Bonsack Machine Company against Allison Brothers Company, Brief on Motion to Dismiss (Box 34)
  - Index of parts, Universal Cigarette Machine (Box 34)
  - Universal Cigarette Machine, photographic catalog of parts (Box 34)
  - Photos, Heckendorn, 1920 (Box 34)
  - Universal Cigarette Machine, photographic catalog of parts (Box 34)
  - United Cigarette Machine Company photographs, 44 8x10 black-and-white prints of cigarette rolling machines (Box 34)
  - The United Cigarette Machine Company Shareholders Minute Book, No. 1, 1900-1916 (Box 35)
  - U.K. cigarette machine, photographic catalog of parts (Box 35)
  - Supreme Court of Missouri: Bonsack Machine Company vs. C.E. Halliwell et al., 1905 (Box 35)
  - Spare parts catalog of the Tobacco Cutting Machine, first edition, In English, German, and French (Box 35)
  - Spare parts catalog of the Cigarette Waste Stripping Machine, first edition, In English, German, and French (Box 35)
- Artifacts Series, early 20th century
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of a model of a cigarette machine, date unknown, but probably from early 20th century.
  - Cigarette rolling machine model, early 20th century (Box 36)